International Typographical Union, No. 15 (Rochester, NY) Records on Microfilm 5667 mf
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
International Typographical Union No. 15 (Rochester, NY) Records on Microfilm
1872-1980
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
International Typographical Union (ITU)
5667 mf
0.67 cubic feet
6 microfilm reels
Records (documents), microfilm.
Meeting minutes, papers and correspondence
3338524
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff, September 26, 2012
EAD encoding:
Kheel Staff, March 25, 2019
Biographical / Historical
The International Typographical Union (ITU) was an US trade union for the printing trade for newspapers and other media. It was founded on May 3rd, 1852 in the United States as the National Typographical Union, and changed its name to the International Typographical Union in 1869 after it began organizing members in Canada.
ITU President W.B. Prescott led the ITU in 1897 to win a 48-hour work week and a standard wage scale for all printers. During the Great Depression, the ITU introduced the 40-hour work week across the industry at no cost to employers as a way to share the fewer jobs available. That ITU initiative spread to other unions and has since been codified across the labor sector by federal legislation in the U.S. establishing the 40-hour work week.
As the work of typographers' declined with automation, computers and mechanization of the print media, the ITU was disbanded. In 1986, a majority of ITU mailers voted to merge with the International Brotherhood of Teamsters and the remaining typographers joined the Communications Workers of America. Before its dissolution, the ITU was the oldest union in the United States.
Scope and Contents
A negative copy is available upon request.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: 5345: International Typographical Union, Local 6 Legal Files 5436: International Typographical Union Local 252 (Binghamton, NY) Minutes and Related Papers 5811: International Typographical Union Local 62 (Utica, NY) Minute Book 5957: International Typographical Union Local 6 Strike Clipping File
Arrangement
Series I: Meeting Minutes, Papers and Correspondence
Series II: Executive Board Minutes
Labor unions -- New York (State) -- Rochester; International Typographical Union of North America.; International Typographical Union of North America. Local 15 (Rochester, N.Y.)
3338524
- Series I: Meeting Minutes, Papers and Correspondence
  - 1872-1878, 1 (Reel 1)
  - 1898-1907, 2 (Reel 1)
  - 1980-August 1916, 1 (Reel 2)
  - Sept., 1916-April, 1924, 2 (Reel 2)
  - May, 1924-1929, 1 (Reel 3)
  - 1930-1932, 2 (Reel 3)
  - 1933-1934, 1 (Reel 4)
  - 1935-1936, 2 (Reel 4)
  - 1938-1939, 3 (Reel 4)
  - 1940-1940, 4 (Reel 4)
  - 1942-1943, 5 (Reel 4)
  - 1944-1945, 6 (Reel 4)
  - 1946-1947, 7 (Reel 4)
  - 1948-1950, 8 (Reel 4)
  - 1951-1953, 9 (Reel 4)
  - 1954-1957, 1 (Reel 5)
  - 1958-1959, 1 (Reel 6)
  - 1960, 2 (Reel 6)
  - 1962, 3 (Reel 6)
  - 1963, 4 (Reel 6)
  - 1964, 5 (Reel 6)
  - 1965, 6 (Reel 6)
  - 1966, 7 (Reel 6)
  - 1967, 8 (Reel 6)
  - 1970, 9 (Reel 6)
  - 1971, 10 (Reel 6)
  - 1972, 11 (Reel 6)
  - 1973, 12 (Reel 6)
  - 1974, 13 (Reel 6)
  - 1975, 14 (Reel 6)
  - 1976-1977, 15 (Reel 6)
  - 1978-1979, 16 (Reel 6)
- Series II: Executive Board Minutes
  - 1923-May, 1924, 17 (Reel 6)
  - June 1924 -1928, 18 (Reel 6)
  - 1931, 19 (Reel 6)
  - 1933-1939, 20 (Reel 6)